Page ninety-nine
and these are in the middle of some very sensitive material in
terms of כשרות. Kashrut. We had looked yesterday at the sources for
at the whole development of the idea of ששים Shishim and recently
at פסוקים Psukim which the גמרא Gemara looked to to be the
basis for either repeat the דף. Daf. All right. Okay. So anyway,
yeah, so it's over דף צ"ט Daf Tzadik Tet 99 and we
were we're going to pick up about thank you about five lines
down. Thank you.
רבינא אמר, Ravina Amar, the line starts with the word דאורייתא. D'Oraisa.
It's actually eight lines down. Okay. And we had just looked at
a number of פסוקים Psukim that served as the basis for the
שיעור Shiur of sixty or a hundred was a שיעור Shiur that
was being offered, which is normally a שיעור Shiur that we're familiar
with in the משניות Mishnayot in זרעים, Zeraim, but does not come
up by כשרות Kashrus issues and we'll see about that in a
minute. So just to refresh where we were up to, we had
seen the משנה Mishna mention that if a גיד הנשה Gid HaNashe
is cooked with, this by the way is the motherload of a
lot of the issues about טעם Ta'am and ששים. Shishim. So the
משנה Mishna had mentioned that if a גיד הנשה Gid HaNashe is
cooked in the thigh without being removed, you have to determine whether
it can be tasted. And even mentioned the idea of determining טעם
Ta'am when it's cooked with all similar things, other גיד, Gid, in
which case טעם Ta'am is not possible. Now how do you determine
טעם Ta'am if you're not allowed to taste? So the משנה Mishna
spoke about a model, about looking at an analogy or whatever a
comparable case of meat was cooked with turnip. That led the גמרא
Gemara to a couple of to basically two sort of if you
would strands. One strand looked at the טעם Ta'am issue and on
the one hand developed the model and spoke not only about the
turnip and the meat but continued considering every forbidden thing as if
it were an onion and determining whether an onion would give טעם,
Ta'am, which is obviously a stringency, but it's a way of playing
it safe and then continuing within the category of טעם, Ta'am, mentioned
the idea had the idea of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan which certainly
opened up the possibilities of having a non-Jew taste it, a non-Jewish
chef, and that was a way to determine טעם. Ta'am. Or if
it's a כשר Kosher thing even have a Jew taste it. So
that was the model of טעם. Ta'am. Alternatively, the גמרא Gemara developed
an idea of using numbers, using the model of sixty as a
way, and there it certainly started to be presented as a stand-in
if you cannot determine טעם. Ta'am. If you can't determine טעם, Ta'am,
what do you do? There's no chef around, or a non-Jew if
you don't need a chef, or whatever, or it's מין במינו Min
BeMino and all tastes the same. What do you do? You use
sixty as a stand-in. If it's less than one-sixtieth, it's not a
problem. And then we saw that there was a whole development of
that, that there were some that were doing that there was a
time when they weren't using one-sixtieth, they were suggesting one-thirtieth for certain
דרבנן Drabbanan or one forty-five, one forty-seven, but eventually
one-sixtieth became the model. So it seems like you have those two
models, the tasting model and then the substitute for טעם, Ta'am, the
שיעור Shiur of one in sixty, and where one in sixty serves
as the fallback or the stand-in and only if you could not
actually determine the טעם. Ta'am. And that by the way I should
repeat is the approach of the ספרדים. Sefardim. The ספרדים Sefardim say
that if you have כשר-טרף stuff cooked with כשר, Kosher what do
you do? You get a non-Jew to taste it under the right
parameters where, you know, you don't have to be worried that they're
trying to trip you up, and then you could rely on it.
And only if for some reason that's not available or because it's
מין במינו Min BeMino and all tastes the same, you use one
in sixty. The אשכנזים Ashkenazim like to to take the approach which
I generally call keep it simple stupid, which is let's not let's
not worry about different cases, let's just have one standard that fits
all, which usually means the most מחמיר Machmir standard, and therefore we
go by one in sixty. That's the basic אשכנזי Ashkenazic approach. What
we had just seen now is in the גמרא Gemara the one
in sixty and the idea of the quantity as being a as
being actually almost given greater weight and based on פסוקים Psukim by
the זרוע בשלה Zroa Beshela by the ram of by the arm
of of the of the ram that was cooked for the שלמים,
Shelamim, we are being told that that tells us the model that
you need one in sixty or according to another opinion one in
a hundred to effect ביטול. Bitul. What does this mean? So רש"י
Rashi says it really means it and it really means independent of
טעם, Ta'am, there's a biblical requirement that something be quantitatively insignificant. So
it's not about being a stand-in for טעם Ta'am and רש"י Rashi
even goes so far to say that it might be that the
concern of טעם Ta'am is not even biblical, that might only be
a rabbinic concern, טעם כעיקר דאורייתא, Ta'am K'Ikar D'Oraisa, and nevertheless there's
a concern that if there's טרף Treif mixed up, it be quantitatively
insignificant. One in sixty, one in a hundred. So that's seeing it
as an independent requirement which is new than we've seen before. תוספות
Tosafot says that this whole גמרא Gemara is an אסמכתא. Asmachta. That
the one in sixty is really a rabbinic way of substituting for
a טעם Ta'am test and we're just using these פסוקים Psukim as
an אסמכתא. Asmachta. Okay with that is a quick background review of
what we've done for the last two days. Yes.
What is מין במינו?
Min BeMino? מין במינו, Min BeMino, like with like. Meaning apples and
apples, as opposed to מין בשאינו מינו, Min Beshe'eino Mino, which is
apples and oranges. So it's apples and apples, meat and meat, there's
no way of testing for the טעם, Ta'am, then and therefore you
can only use something like a one in a sixty type of
a test. Okay.
So now, yes? But it's very interesting. I mean, you know, you
said it's basically quantitatively as well as relative, but which means that
you can have a huge amount. If you're making this big, big,
big vat, you could also have a huge amount of non-kosher in
there.
Sure, as long as it's as long as it's
proportionally insignificant and it gets mixed up. If it's in a clump
and you can see it, you're required to remove it. We're talking
here that it's completely dispersed. Okay. So now the גמרא, Gemara, learning
it out from the זרוע בשלה, zero'a beshelah, is just bothered with
the fact that there was a line that says that that whole
case of the arm cooked with the ram was a special exception,
special leniency, and then it was trying to figure out, well, if
it's a leniency, what was the leniency and why can we learn
from it? So now the גמרא Gemara picks up finally where the
line starts with the word דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, middle of the line, רבינא
אמר. Ravina Amar. רבינא Ravina says, לא נצרכה אלא למקום חתך. lo
nitzrecha ela limkom chatech. So this special leniency of the arm with
the ram has nothing to do with ביטול bitul and therefore is
not relevant to our concerns. The fact that it's labeled as a
leniency is referring to the place where it was cut. דאמר מקום
חתך בתר אמא שדי d'amar makom chatech batar amma shadi because it's
basically saying that normally where you cut off a forbidden thing, it's
normally forbidden. והכא שרי. ve-hacha shari. Here it's permitted. What does this
mean? So you'll all remember, of course, like, you know, when we
were in קדשים, Kodashim, the גמרא Gemara loved to go back to
פיגול. pigul. Well, here the גמרא Gemara sometimes, like one of the
more fascinating things that the גמרא Gemara seems to like to go
back to is the whole fetus with the arm stuck out, or
the fetus in the mother's womb. So if you remember the fetus
with the arm stuck out, you can't eat that arm. Well, what
happens if you cut off the arm? What happens exactly at the
place where it's cut off? The place where, as רש"י Rashi describes,
is not in the womb, but it's not outside the womb, it's
right sort of, you know, at the thickness of the walls of
the womb. So, and the way the גמרא Gemara conceptually explains that
question is: Is it if it's outside of the womb, it's no
good? Or is it that it needs to be in the womb
to be permitted through the mother's שחיטה? shechitah? And what do you
do exactly at that place that's exactly in that grey zone, exactly
on the line? So there it says normally we would be strict
about the place of the cutting and require that exactly at that
place it be not good, whereas, I don't know how thick that
space is, but here we would be lenient, meaning that if the
תורה Torah says you cook the ram with the arm and then,
or forget whether you cooked it, you cut off the arm and
you give it to the כהן, Kohen, and that arm, as we
said, cannot be eaten by a non-כהן, Kohen, well, what about exactly
at the place where the arm connected to the body? Is that
part of the arm or part of the body? Exactly at the
place of connection. So maybe I have to be strict and give
that exact place of connection to the כהן Kohen as well because
maybe it's part of the arm. So it says, no, no, no,
here you just give the arm. You don't have to worry about
the exact place of connection. תוספות Tosafos says this is really true
by all קדשים Kodashim because there's other things you give to the
כהן. Kohen. You give to the כהן, Kohen, you know, the the
the the side and the and the chest from a שלמים shlamim
and so on. So תוספות Tosafos says there too, but what the
תורה's Torah just saying is, remove this and give this to the
כהן. Kohen. So it's the thing you remove that you have to
give. You don't have to worry about that grey zone where it's
connected. It's not like the part of the body that is the
arm belongs to the כהן. Kohen. It's: Remove the arm and give
the arm to the כהן. Kohen. So it's what... need special pasuk?
No. So תוספות Tosafos actually says you don't need a פסוק pasuk
because normally the תורה... Torah... Right. I know. Well, no, that's different.
You could say play safe. But תוספות Tosafos says you don't need
a פסוק. pasuk. תוספות Tosafos just says by logic, if the תורה
Torah says give the breast, give the thigh, give the arm, it
means cut it off and give it. You don't have to worry
about the space that's neither arm nor body, but exactly the place
of connection. Okay? So that's what, that's what this is saying, and
therefore it's not really relevant to our concerns. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes back. יתיב רב דימי. Yasiv Rav Dimi. So רב
דימי Rav Dimi was sitting וקאמר לה להאי שמעתא ve-ka'amar lah le-hai
shema'ata and he was telling over this discussion. אמר ליה אביי. Amar
lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye said to him: וכל איסורין שבתורה במאה?
ve-chol issurin she-ba-Torah be-me'ah? How could there be an opinion that says
you normally require ביטול bitul of a hundred? והתנן, Ve-ha tnan, we
taught in a משנה. Mishnah. Okay, and now we're going to see
that, and again as I mentioned to you, in the משניות Mishnayos
you never hear of a number used for ביטול bitul by normal
איסור. issur. The only place you hear of a number, the only
thing you hear in the משניות Mishnayos is taste, or if you
hear of a number, it's like one in a hundred and it's
by certain cases of like of תרומה, Terumah,
ערלה, Orlah, certain cases about certain agricultural cases where you hear one
in a hundred, there even one in two hundred. Okay, but in
normal איסורים issurim you never hear one in a hundred, you only
hear taste. And that's essentially what אביי Abaye is now going to
ask. How can you say that even for normal איסורים issurim you
need one in a hundred? That's a number that we use by
other things and that's a more str- and that specifically is a
greater stringency than the normal rule, where the normal rule is taste.
So let's take a look. והתנן, Ve-ha tnan, we taught in a
משנה Mishnah by ערלה. Orlah. למה אמרו כל המחמץ והמטבל והמדמע להחמיר?
lamah amru kol ha-mechametz ve-ha-metabel ve-ha-medameh lehachmir? In what situations do they
say that anything that is מחמץ, mechametz, that leavens, or מטבל, metabel,
spices, or מדמע, medameh, or is a mixture, just a simple mixture?
And here we're talking about תרומה Terumah with other things and the
rule of תרומה Terumah is you need one in a hundred to
so-called ביטול. bitul. So in what case... In what cases do they
say that those were problems, or what are the parameters of those
problems? So להחמיר מין במינו, Lehachmir Min Be'mino, להקל ולהחמיר מין ושאינו
מינו. Lehakel U'lehachmir Min Vesheino Mino, So it is strict in a
case of מין במינו, Min Be'mino, and it can be strict or
lenient in a case of מין ושאינו מינו, Min Vesheino Mino. apples
and oranges. Now, what does this mean? I'm going to tell you
what this means outside, because it gets a little confusing reading it
inside. Here's what it means. The basic Rabbinic idea that you need
a שיעור, Shiur, a more stringent amount than taste, you need a
one in a hundred, one in a 200, was only said by
like and like. Now, that's a little bit strange, because like and
like normally we say there's not even taste, there's nothing to worry
about. So let me take a step back and sort of frame
the issues about מין במינו Min Be'mino, and מין ושאינו מינו. Min
Vesheino Mino, Like and unlike, apples and oranges, okay, מין ושאינו מינו,
Min Vesheino Mino. are things where there's one basic way of measuring,
you know, is there still a presence of the thing, assuming that
it's not separate and identifiable, and that is: can it still be
tasted? So there the taste is king. The basic question is, is
there טעם Ta'am or not טעם, Ta'am, and if we're not using
טעם, Ta'am, we'll use something like one in 60 as a stand-in
for טעם. Ta'am. That's where you have the potential of different tastes,
apples and oranges. Let's say you have apples and apples, מין במינו.
Min Be'mino So there's no potential of taste. So in this you
can go to opposite extremes. One extreme you could say is, it's
automatically בטל Battel as long as there's a simple majority, so there's
a majority of kosher apples over non-kosher apples or whatever it is,
so you know, it's בטל Battel because there's nothing else to make
the to make this prohibited thing make its presence felt. So it's
purely quantitative. You could go, that's מין במינו בטל ברוב. Min Be'mino
Battel Berov. That's the basic assumption our גמרא's Gemara been working with.
Then you could go to the other extreme of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and say since there's no way it can lose its identity,
its identity is always there, there's always apples here, you can't say
the apples have gone away because it's always apples. So because it
can't lose its identity, it's always there, that's רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
position, מין במינו Min Be'mino. is not בטל. Battel. There's also a
possible middle position, which is what the רמב"ם Rambam says, which is
the, or the way the רמב"ם Rambam articulates it, the רמב"ם Rambam
doesn't say it, which is called
בטל מעוצם מיעוטו. Battel Me'otzem Mi'uto. It becomes nullified through its extreme
minuteness, its extreme insignificance, which means you don't, it can lose its
identity not by the sense of like identity, like it was tastable
now it can't be tasted because it is all just apples, but
it can lose its identity because it's quantitatively insignificant. Okay? And therefore
it's not a simple majority 51 percent, but it's not it's never
בטל Battel if it becomes quantitatively insignificant. And then you have to
figure out what is that quantitative insignificance, okay, at one in 60,
one in 100, what is it? The reason I say this is
the following: this plays out
where normally we're much more lenient by מין במינו. Min Be'mino We
say biblically it's בטל ברוב Battel Berov and even when you need
60, that's only a Rabbinic requirement, and so normally we take this
end of the spectrum and we're much more lenient. But there is
a place where we're more strict and we recognize the possible stringencies
of מין במינו, Min Be'mino. and that's when it comes to things
like תרומה Terumah and ערלה Orlah and things that we demand higher
numbers to create ביטול Bittul because they're more severe. And there we
chose, if we're going to demand one in 100, one in 200,
higher numbers to create ביטול, Bittul, we're only going to demand it
by מין במינו, Min Be'mino, not by מין ושאינו מינו, Min Vesheino
Mino, which seems ironic, but it speaks to the dual nature of
מין במינו. Min Be'mino, מין ושאינו מינו Min Vesheino Mino, automatically is
בטל Battel when its taste can no longer be tasted. That says
that it's lost its identity, right? It's like, you know, when somebody's
completely acclimated, completely assimilated to the outside society, they started different and
now they look like everybody else around them, it completely lost its
identity. So we can't demand more by מין ושאינו מינו, Min Vesheino
Mino it's already lost its identity. But by מין במינו Min Be'mino.
we can there look at it through a different lens and say,
oh, it didn't lose its identity, it's the same as it was,
and there we can demand higher, in certain cases, we can say
you need one in 100, one in 200. So the upshot of
this is that as a general rule, מין במינו Min Be'mino we're
much more lenient. It's only Rabbinic that we require more than majority.
But in cases where we're going to demand things like one in
100, one in 200, we're going to be more strict by מין
במינו Min Be'mino than we are by מין ושאינו מינו. Min Vesheino
Mino, Okay? So that's the background. I hope that made it clearer.
Now we're going to read this in the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה's
Mishnah going to say that when it comes to like and unlike,
apples and oranges, you only go by taste. When it comes to
like and like, there, regardless of taste, you need one in 100.
Okay? This is by cases where we demand one in 100 like
תרומה. Terumah. So let's take a look. והתנן, Vehatnan, no, let's read
it. ולמה אמרו, Velamah Amru, כל המחמץ ומתבל ומדמע, Kol Hamchameitz U'metavel
U'medamei, להחמיר Lehachmir מין במינו, Min Be'mino when it comes to like
and like we are
strict, להקל ולהחמיר Lehakel U'lehachmir מין ושאינו מינו, Min Vesheino Mino. if
it's like and unlike, apples and
oranges.
This is all by תרומה. Terumah. וקתני סיפא, U'katani Seifa, and we
taught at the end to explain this, להקל ולהחמיר מין ושאינו מינו
כיצד? Lehakel U'lehachmir Min Vesheino Mino Keitzad? How are we sometimes strict
and sometimes lenient by like and unlike, apples and
oranges? So, גריסין שנתבשלו עם העדשים, Grisin Shenitbashlu Im Ha'adashim, so you
cooked the גריסין, Grisin, I don't know
what they... Not necessarily the first things I would have put in
in like and unlike categories, just don't sit on my jacket there.
Anyway, somehow these are different types, they're apples and oranges, maybe for
people that are sensitive to the taste, people, some people say apples
and oranges are all fruit. Okay, so anyway, split peas and lentils,
green beans, let's say, I don't know, green peas and lentils. Anyway,
these are that's apples and oranges. So you cook them together, and
one of them is תרומה terumah and the other is not תרומה.
terumah. אם יש בהם בנותן טעם, Im yesh bahem b'nosein ta'am, if
you can taste it, בין יש בהן להעלות במאה ואחד בין אין
בהן להעלות במאה ואחד, bein yesh bahem l'haalos b'meia v'echad bein ein
bahem l'haalos b'meia v'echad, whether you have a hundred and one or
not a hundred and one. A hundred and one means including the
forbidden thing, meaning a hundred opposite it. So אסור, assur, it is
forbidden. Meaning, I don't care if you have the, I don't care
about the numbers. I don't care about a hundred or not a
hundred. What I care about if it's apples and oranges is can
you taste it? If it's beans and lentils, I care can you
taste it? Okay, the numbers are insignificant. אין בהם בנותן טעם, Ein
bahem b'nosein ta'am, and if it does not have, if it cannot
be tasted, if it can be tasted it's a problem, if it
can't be tasted, בין יש בהן להעלות במאה ואחד בין אין בהן
להעלות במאה ואחד מותר. bein yesh bahem l'haalos b'meia v'echad bein ein
bahem l'haalos b'meia v'echad mutar. Then whether it has one hundred or
not one hundred is permissible. Meaning, when it's apples and oranges, it
all goes by taste. It doesn't go by number. Okay, that's what
we said. When it goes with like and unlike, taste is king.
And if you can, if you can taste it, it's a problem,
you can't taste it, it loses its identity. So the whole thing
that we demand one in a hundred, or a hundred opposite it,
by תרומה, terumah, is only by like and like. As I said,
מין במינו min b'mino can be very lenient, but it can also
be very strict because you don't have the measure of taste. And
if you don't have the measure of taste, you can say you
don't need anything essentially, or you can say no, no, no, you
need a lot, you need a hundred times it, you need some
number in order to make it בטל. batel. Let's just read that
and then I'll take the question.
Okay, דאיירי, de-airy, oh, okay, anyway, I didn't finish. So now we're
going to switch. By the way, it's going to say, we're going
to quote the end of this משנה mishna in a minute, and
the end of the משנה mishna is going to say, but if
it's like and like, then you need to accomplish two things. First
of all, it can't be tasted, although who can really taste by
like and like? But anyway, but if it's like and like, what
that's where the issue of one in a hundred matters. When taste
is not relevant, that's where you're always going to need one in
a hundred, whether in theory it would be tastable or not, it's
all the same, so you're always going to need one in a
hundred. Yeah, there was a question Charlie?
I was going to say if there's no difference in taste, how
could it be like and unlike, two unlikes?
What do you mean? Like and unlike is only with differences in
taste. So this גריסין grisin and עדשים adashim we're assuming have different
taste. Okay.
Like what was asked before, what did you say the ביטול bitul
for חמץ chametz before פסח Pesach was? Is that also just...
I'm not talking about חמץ chametz פסח. Pesach. That's a whole separate
סוגיא suggya because that violates the general rule. Okay, fine. All right,
so now, so now what have we seen? We have seen that
it says that once you solve the taste problem, you don't need
to use the hundred שיעור. shiur. Okay, you don't need to go
by the hundred which is the basic measure by תרומה. terumah. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: מותר. mutar. אין בהן להעלות במאה ואחד. Ein
bahem l'haalos b'meia v'echad.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: so if it does, you
don't have a hundred against it, a hundred and one against it,
אלא במאי? ela bemai? לאו בשישים? Lav b'shishim?
Now of course this is a little bit ironic. The משנה mishna
says if it's apples and oranges you don't need one in a
hundred even if it's תרומה terumah and as long as there's no
taste it's okay. So you think end of story, no taste, right?
All the משניות mishnayos are basically about taste. But remember the גמרא
Gemara now is assuming that there's this demand of sixty or a
hundred and that this demand it's pre-assuming is present already in the
משניות, mishnayos, which is very strange because the way we've learned before
this סוגיא, suggya, which was very clear, is that the משניות mishnayos
demand getting rid of taste and sixty becomes a stand-in for taste.
But what the גמרא Gemara has done since yesterday has introduced the
idea that sixty is an independent requirement based on a פסוק, pasuk,
sixty or a hundred, and now it's going to assume that that
requirement must be present in the משניות. mishnayos. So it's saying, how
could this משנה mishna say that if you don't have taste it's
okay without a hundred? What number do you have if you don't
have a hundred assuming you need a number, assuming taste is not
enough? So it must be the number you need if it's not
a hundred it's sixty. So this משנה mishna proves that the right
number is sixty not a hundred. Because here it's saying that when
you don't when you don't have taste it's okay with a number
that isn't a hundred. So the only number that could be that
isn't a hundred is sixty. So it shows that sixty is the
right number. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, במאה. lo, b'meia. No,
maybe the number you have is a hundred. Now we've got a
little problem. Because it said a hundred is what we're strict about
by תרומה. terumah. By תרומה terumah we demand a hundred. So now
it says: oh, if it's about apples and oranges you don't need
the strict number of a hundred by תרומה terumah you just need
to get rid of taste. Now we're assuming there's got to be
another number. So we're
saying... So how can you say that you have a number of
a hundred? So the גמרא Gemara says והתני רישא במאה הוי ve-hatni
reisha be-me'ah havei when you do when you are strict by תרומה
terumah you demand a hundred סיפא בשישים seifa be-shishim
so it must be when you're not strict when it's apples and
oranges then the number you need is not a hundred but a
sixty דקתני רישא dikteni reisha the beginning of the משנה mishnah
teaches להחמיר מין במינו כיצד le-hachmir min b'mino keitzad how are we
always strict when it's like and like apples and apples שאור של
חטים שנפל לעיסת חטים se'or shel chittin she-nafal le-issat chittin you have
yeast that is made of wheat flour that fell into wheat dough
okay so it's all wheat ויש בו כדי לחמץ ve-yesh bo kedei
le-chametz and there's enough that it can make it make it
ferment so taste and fermentation are essentially the same if it can
give off taste right and that by the way is how you
can have a concept of taste even by like and like even
by apples and apples it can't be tasted but it might have
the power to make it ferment okay so that's how you can
have both of those things to consider because fermenting is like tasting
its impact can be felt so if there's enough to make it
ferment so בין יש בו כדי להעלות במאה ואחד בין אין בו
כדי להעלות במאה ואחד ben yesh bo kedei le-halot be-me'ah ve-echad ben
ein bo kedei le-halot be-me'ah ve-echad whether there's a hundred and one
or not a hundred and one who cares about the numbers אסור
assur if its impact can be felt then it's forbidden that's like
it can be tasted essentially אין בו להעלות במאה ואחד ein bo
le-halot be-me'ah ve-echad and the opposite is also true if it doesn't
have a hundred opposite it בין יש בו כדי לחמץ בין אין
בו כדי לחמץ ben yesh bo kedei le-chametz ben ein bo kedei
le-chametz whether it can make the ferment the dough or not אסור
assur it's also forbidden so the אפשט upshat of this is what
when you have like and like you always need the number hundred
what you also need to do is if in the case of
like and like where the impact can be felt it won't be
by taste but let's say by fermenting you have to make it
that the impact can't be felt it can't be able to ferment
but bracketing the fermenting issue the basic point here is by apples
and apples by by wheat and wheat what you need is the
number of one in a hundred
yeah but it didn't work what I said it didn't work
without one in a hundred if it can be fermented the numbers
don't matter and if you have the number and if you don't
have the numbers non-fermenting doesn't matter you need to do both A
you can't feel its impact can't be ferment and B you always
need the numbers so again let's take a step back because it's
getting a little complicated here's the basic rule by תרומה terumah where
we demand one in a hundred which is a stringency by תרומה
terumah we only demand it by like and like so like and
unlike the whole measure is apples and oranges beans and barley or
whatever it is the measure is it can't be tasted okay we
always go by taste like and like wheat and wheat you need
one in a hundred you also need that it can't feel its
impact it can't ferment but let's bracket that you always need one
in a hundred so on the one hand it goes
by
taste and by apples and apples it goes by one in a
hundred so now we are saying like this by the case of
apples and oranges it said it can't be tasted now it would
seem that that's the end but the גמרא Gemara is assuming there's
got to also be a number we're working here with the assumption
that there's also a number going around and it's not just about
tasting and it says that number has to be sixty in this
case where we're saying you don't have to worry about the hundred
that's in this case of apples and oranges here you just have
to worry about taste okay so if the גמרא Gemara wants to
insert a number the taste of the number is going to have
to be sixty because if you say the number is a hundred
then it's exactly as strict as the other case so that's the
גמרא's Gemara question so
they wouldn't be there the משנה mishnah would not be discriminating between
the two exactly if it were a hundred but why wouldn't it
be two hundred rather than sixty
no no no because the משנה mishnah said this case is lenient
all right right right this
case is lenient all you need to worry about is taste this
case you need a hundred so if this case all you have
to worry about is taste and the גמרא Gemara wants to say
oh taste is also a number going on it says you see
the number is
sixty because if the number were a hundred it would be exactly
like the other case
so it must be ninety
yes but the only two options we have right now are sixty
and a hundred okay so is that pretty clear to people another
way of sort of saying this much more simply is you know
is we only know of the number of a hundred by things
like תרומה terumah and ערלה orlah and so on we never know
about it in the world of איסור issur so how can you
introduce the number of a hundred into the world of איסור issur
if we know that it doesn't exist if we know that it
only is present over there in that world of תרומה terumah which
is more or less what the גמרא Gemara is saying okay so
let's take a look at what the גמרא's Gemara answer is so
the גמרא Gemara
says רישא וסיפא במאה reisha ve-seifa be-me'ah so how can both the
beginning and the end be with a hundred if the strict case
is a hundred the lenient case can't be a hundred the lenient
case has to be a different number so the גמרא Gemara says
לא רישא במאה וחד וסיפא במאה lo reisha be-me'ah ve-chad ve-seifa be-me'ah
so until big difference until now the משנה mishnah has been saying
a hundred and one we've assumed that a hundred and one meant
a hundred and one including the forbidden object So there's a hundred
opposite the forbidden object. Here what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
well actually there's רש"י Rashi and תוספות' Tosafos way of reading it.
I'll read it like תוספות' Tosafos way. תוספות Tosafos says that when
we have said, when we are strict by תרומה Terumah and we
need 101, that the 101 total, the forbidden object plus a hundred
opposite. When we have said yesterday that there's an opinion that by
normal איסורין issurin you needed a hundred, we meant a hundred not
of היתר, heter, we meant a hundred total: one of איסור issur
and ninety-nine of היתר. heter. 99. So the big difference between, right,
the world of איסורין issurin and the world of תרומה, Terumah, תרומה
Terumah we demand a hundred, and here we don't, because here all
we demand is 99, okay?
And similarly in the משנה, Mishnah, the big difference between whether it's
apples and oranges or apples and apples is when it's apples and
apples we demand a hundred, when it's apples and oranges we only
demand 99. So that's the גמרא's Gemara answer, which is a very
not satisfying answer. It's not at all surprising that the opinion of
100 for normal איסורין issurin is completely rejected. Okay, because the basic
force of the גמרא Gemara is, the whole idea of 100 is
an idea we find by things like תרומה Terumah and ערלה orlah
and כלאים, kilayim, even 200 there. We do not find that here.
This the most you're going to get up to is 60. Okay,
and that although the גמרא Gemara doesn't completely reject it, it really
does put it to rest. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara just
wraps this discussion up.
This is just an answer or a question?
Yeah, that's it. We're happy with 100 versus 99.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, how does this resolve everything we
said before? What? The גמרא Gemara isn't bothered by that?
How does it resolve everything we said before?
Because you know that means you have no ששים. shishim.
Okay, according to that opinion you don't have ששים, shishim, but we
just don't rule that way. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara just
has one final question. וכי יש בו כדי לחמץ במאה ואחד אמאי
לא בטל? v'chi yesh bo k'dei l'chameitz b'meiah v'achad amai lo batel?
So the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get it. The גמרא Gemara
says, if something is literally one in a hundred, remember the scenario
by the yeast was there was a hundred opposite, 101 total, and
it had enough to ferment, and we're saying that's still a problem
because it can still be felt. So the גמרא Gemara says, how
should that matter if you have a hundred against it? Who cares
that it has some fermenting ability? Which is basically a way of
saying that it's not really going to ferment that much if there's
a hundred against it. So its presence is very trivial. So if
you have a hundred against it, who should care that it has
a little bit of, you know, pungency still left to it? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אישתוק, ishtik, he was silent. He didn't know
how to respond. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back, the
one who asked the question, דילמא שאני שאור דחימוצו קשה, dilma shani
se'or dechimutzo kasheh,
maybe שאור, se'or, which is sourdough, is different because its fermenting ability
is very strong, and maybe even when there's a hundred against it,
maybe it really can have some real ability to ferment. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so he said back to him, אדכרתן מילתא, adkartan milta,
you reminded me of something דאמר רב יוסף בר חנינא. de'amar Rav
Yosef bar Chanina. Because רב יוסף בר חנינא Rav Yosef bar Chanina
said, לא כל השיעורין שוין. lo kol hashi'urin shavin. You can't, after
we answer this big thing about 100 and 60 and whatever, you
can't have a total rule that applies in all cases. Now that
means להחמיר. l'hachmir. This is like when we learned it yesterday,
Charlie, and you said like what about pepper, what about spices? So
this is what we're saying now, that even if we develop a
number like 60 or 100 or whatever that number is, sometimes there
will be things that are very pungent and you can't ignore them
even when you've satisfied the number. So that's why even though, yes,
the number 60 and that's an assumption by all things, if you're
dealing with spices obviously you know you can't rely on 60. If
you're doing with yeast, you might not be able to rely on
it. Or nowadays you know they have, you know, artificial flavors or
natural flavors, right? It's like a tiny, tiny percentage, but they've developed
the science that it can be felt even though it's a trivial
amount of the material. So those are different. By the way, I
should say that those are the most dangerous things on the ingredients
are where natural flavors. Because natural flavors, people think oh it's natural,
it's from some type of fruit or whatever. You know what a
lot of natural flavors come from? Tell us Charlie. Ground insects. What?
Insects? Ground up ants, right. Little ants. And those can be tasted.
The whole reason they put natural flavors in is so it can
be tasted even though it's a tiny amount. So that's where שיעורין
shi'urin numbers don't matter. Let's just read through the end.
לא כל השיעורין שוין. lo kol hashi'urin shavin. ציר, tzir, which is
like
the fish brine, thank you, שיעורו קרוב למאתים. shi'uro karov l'masayim. We
normally need up to close to 200 to make it בטל. batel.
דתנן, detnan, דג טמא צירו אסור, dag tamei tziro assur, a non-kosher
fish, the brine is forbidden. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, and
here's the שיעור, shi'ur, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רביעית בסאתים.
revi'is b'sasayim. You have a רביעית revi'is of it, like three ounces,
you would need סאתים sasayim to be בטל. batel. And I won't
do the math for you, but it's basically 192. Okay, you need
192 times it to create
ביטול. bitul. והאמר veha'amar רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda מין במינו לא בטיל?
min b'mino lo batil? How could he say that? He just says
it's not בטל batel in a, this is the same רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that says like and like is not בטל. batel. So
presumably he means brine with other brine. Now how the גמרא Gemara
knows he means other brine, I don't know. Maybe he meant something
else. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says שאני ציר דזיעה בעלמא הוא.
shani tzir dezei'ah b'alma hu. He's lenient by fish brine because fish
brine is not the real fish, it's just like literally the sweat
or you know, the not the real thing itself. And therefore it's
only rabbinic and he's willing to be lenient. Now I just want
to make two comments about that. First of all, זיעה בעלמא, ze'iva
b'alma, when is something considered the thing itself or not? תוספות Tosafot
says we also have a הלכה halacha that you have the brine
or the ציר, tzir, whatever the juices that come out of non-kosher
meat and there we have a פסוק pasuk that tells you that
that's דאורייתא de'oraita forbidden, so there's different standards whether do we consider
like the juices that run off to be the same biblical prohibition.
By the way, it's pretty funny because if טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar
is biblical, then you would imagine that the brine that comes off
is certainly biblical if it has the same taste. But again, maybe
there's different degrees. Is it the exact same איסור, issur, a different
איסור? issur? So there's those types of questions. This issue of ציר
בעלמא tzir b'alma also comes up a lot פסח Pesach time, because
what's the story with alcohol, you know grain alcohol? So some people
say it's חמץ גמור chametz gamur and some people say it might
be permitted because it's זיעה בעלמא. ze'iva b'alma. You know, it's basically
just liquid with a little bit of flavor or maybe it's טעם
כעיקר ta'am k'ikar like the סוגיא sugya we're learning about. So those
are issues. The question about how do you measure זיעה ze'iva and
how זיעה ze'iva is similar or not similar to the general questions
of טעם ta'am is a whole separate category. The other comment to
make here is that it's quite bizarre is that if you're saying
that you have to be concerned that sometimes the numbers don't do
the job because its impact can be felt, I don't get it.
If it's מין במינו, min be'mino, how can the impact be felt?
Right? I mean, it's one thing to say that something like sourdough,
it all tastes the same but it has the ability to ferment.
You can call it מינו mino and the impact can be felt.
But if it's brine and brine, so I don't get it, and
if it's different flavored brine, if it tastes different, then it's not
מין במינו. min be'mino. So what was the question according to רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? So that's a little bit strange, I don't really
know the answer. But the basic point is is that even when
you have the numbers of one in sixty or whatever numbers you
have, if you have something that is very pungent, very tasty, or
other ways like you have מעמיד ma'amid which we haven't gotten to
yet, things like things that cause fermenting, things that cause give it
form like gelatin, things that impact can be felt, then even when
you have the numbers you can't just go by the numbers, you
have to pay attention to that. And that's essentially that there's the
טעם ta'am idea. Certainly the numbers certainly does not
overwhelm, eradicate, efface the whole concern of טעם. ta'am. טעם ta'am is
a reality and if it's there you have to worry about it.
There was one or two quick questions there. Yeah.
That actually was my question about appearance. A bit out of a
ground up ant could create a red tone.
That's an interesting question too, חזותא. chazuta. If חזותא chazuta and if
things like food coloring, to what degree are those problems? That's an
interesting question that's also discussed in the פוסקים, poskim, yeah. Yeah, Seth?
I don't know if this is apples and oranges, but is this
where like onions, mustard, this comes out of?
Oh, a דבר חריף davar charif when you cut it with a
sharp knife? No, that's a different concern. When you cut things with
a sharp knife, by the way, if it's mustard and not mustard
seed that's not a חריף charif problem because you need also the
cutting pressure of the knife and there you just use the knife
to scoop it out. But no, that's a separate discussion which we
will get into.
This is, this is not, this could also be a sweet taste,
it could be I don't know cinnamon or something, so yeah it's
a different concern. This is just that it's a very pungent taste.
I just want to understand just where we are in terms of
these different numbers and whatnot because now we're talking about a hundred
but you're saying that's according to that opinion?
Right, so let me sum it up.
Yeah, I will sum it up.
So here's the sum up. By cases like תרומה trumah or ערלה,
orlah, things you will almost never see in your life unless you're
living in Israel, the numbers might be one in a hundred and
one in two hundred when it's מין במינו, min be'mino, like and
like. That's when we're more strict with like and like. But מין
בשאינו מינו, min b'she'eino mino, you still go by taste. Okay, but
that's by things like ערלה orlah and תרומה. trumah. Things that we're
going to encounter in our life, the basic ruling is taste by
אינו מינו, eino mino, apples and oranges, it's a biblical concern let's
say according to the consensus. טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar is דאורייתא. de'oraita.
By, so the taste of something is considered like the thing itself,
whether fully like the thing is a discussion. But anyway, so that's
if it's something like a piece of חזיר chazir in your potato
stew. If it's like and like, apples and apples, non-kosher meat with
your kosher meat, so that is considered to be that biblically it's
enough to have a majority. דרבנן, drabbanan, we make it similar to
the other category and we require that you also have sixty, one
in sixty. By the אינו מינו, eino mino, do you go by
taste, do you go by numbers? The whole סוגיא sugya we learned
here seems to emphasize numbers as an independent criteria. That's רש"י's Rashi
position. רש"י Rashi says you need to adjust both taste and number.
The ספרדים Sefardim basically say no no no, this is all אסמכתא
asmachta and really the issue is taste and if you get a
non-Jew to taste it. If you don't have that available, then you
use the number. The אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, while they agree in principle that
the עיקר ikar is taste, or at least it seems they do,
still say that as a rule we're always going to go by
one in sixty and they don't like having other people taste it
unless in certain cases of emergency.
Yeah. By טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar of איסור והיתר, issur v'heter, does
the same principles apply in בשר וחלב? basar v'chalav? Pretty much. We'll
talk about it when we get to the next section.
What was confusing was this ninety-nine thing. So what was that?
Forget about that. That's according to the opinion that said by
normal איסורים. issurim. No, things that give shape, מעמיד, ma'amid, is not
discussed in the גמרא, Gemara, it is a major מחלוקת machlokes I
mean there is a גמרא Gemara that deals with it but in
a special case it is a major מחלוקת ראשונים, machlokes rishonim, some
say it is not a problem at all and some say that
it is a problem even במשהו be'mashehu and some say it is
a difference between בשר בחלב basar be'chalav and other things.
So what
do we do?
We will talk about it when we get to it. There is
a whole other, there is a whole rest of חולין Chulin to
get to. Okay, so let's now take a look.
Okay, actually to wrap this up I will tell for the sake
because I told it over ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and not everybody
heard it. So just just to wrap up this story this with
this great story that I tell my students about this difference between
the ספרדי Sephardi and the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach. So those who already
heard it excuse me but anyway there was a case where somebody
there was a huge like wedding and a huge amount of food
and something טרף Treif I was told it was a real story,
I don't know anyway something טרף treif fell in and it would
have like ruined it for everybody. So what were they going to
do? So they didn't know if there was sixty or not sixty.
So they had a non-Jew come over and they asked him to
taste it and they said, "Can you taste it?" He said, "No."
So says, "Okay great. That works for ספרדים Sephardim because ספרדים Sephardim
trust a non-Jew." So then they asked a ספרדי Sephardi to come
over and they had that, "You can eat this now, you taste
it." So he ate it. "Can you taste it?" "No." So says,
"Great. Now we בדיעבד be'di'eved אשכנזים Ashkenazim will trust the tasting of
a Jew but not of a non-Jew. So now we can trust
this and now we can go ahead and eat it too." So
that is how, so anyway, so that is a not a bad
trick to use if but
but yes but that is an issue that does come up because
there is a general question about, you know, at least from the
גמרא's Gemara concern, the גמרא Gemara was always concerned that non-Jews were
trying to trip them up. And it is interesting here that the
basic position is that you can trust a non-Jew, again it might
be under special circumstances, he doesn't know you're relying on them, he's
a chef or whatever. But because it went against, that goes against
certain other attitudes in other גמרות, Gemaros, that's partly is what informs
the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach that basically is you don't you know maybe
you can trust Jews בדיעבד be'di'eved in this case but you don't
want to rely on the tasting of a non-Jew. I should mention
one also, I should mention also an interesting question about what type
of taste are we talking about. Let's say you can detect a
faint presence of something but it doesn't really taste like the thing
itself. How much does it have to have the original taste, right?
Let's say because something is there, you know, there was a catalyst
and it caused, you know, whatever, not a catalyst but whatever, you
know, combined with other tastes and now there is a brand new
taste but it doesn't taste like the original thing. The general assumption
is that that's not a problem at all although yeah although that
is also not fully clear.
Is there a historical reason to that? Do ספרדים Sephardim have a
better relationship?
Well that is interesting to wonder about, you know, because אשכנזים Ashkenazim
lived amongst a hostile non-Jewish population, amongst the Christians, you know, period
that suffered through the Crusades and in general it was pretty hostile.
And the ספרדים Sephardim lived through a very, well not all the
ספרדים Sephardim because you know, but but certainly in the time when
they lived amongst the Muslims it was a very welcoming type of
a of you know of an environment. Eventually when they did they,
you know, then then the Reconquista and then they were did live
under Christian Spain but and a lot of the opinions of the
ספרדים Sephardim that are articulated here were are when they're living in
Christian Spain. But nevertheless, you know, one does wonder if that maybe
did have did have some impact. I'm not sure that's the whole
thing. I really think a lot of it has to do with
the fact that the אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, I really don't think the big
difference is Jew versus non-Jew. They don't even really like relying on
Jews for the taste. They just it's really about having a standard
of one in sixty, standard, just follow it all the time, you
know, don't go case by case. Yes. Okay let's take a look
now. כיצד משערים. keitzad meshaarim. Okay how do you determine it? This
גיד gid that was cooked with the meat. So אמר רב הונא
כבשר בראשי לפתות, amar Rav Huna ke'basar be'roshei liftot, it said meat
amongst turnips. So he says meat with the heads of turnips. What
are the heads of turnips? So רש"י Rashi says it means the
top and תוספות Tosafot says it means the bottom, the roots. Okay
and there's question is that being more strict or more lenient? רש"י
Rashi says it's being more lenient because the heads of the turnips
are more able to again remember רש"י Rashi says that the stand-in
for the גיד gid is the meat and the turnips is the
stand-in for the rest of the pot so רש"י Rashi says the
heads of the turnips are more able to absorb the taste, you
know, and disperse the taste than the bottom of the turnip. I
don't know. תוספות Tosafot says roots.
The bottom is very hard. What? The bottom of the turnip is
very hard.
The head is
very soft.
So they absorb more.
So that the bottom, well it depends if we're being lenient or
strict.
Yes. Well the גיד gid is kind of hard too.
Oh that's interesting. Okay anyway but again according to רש"י Rashi it's
not clear in the גמרא, Gemara, I would have suggested the opposite,
but according to רש"י Rashi the בשר basar is representing the גיד,
gid, the turnip is representing the rest of the pot. Okay מתניתין
דלא כהאי תנא, matnisin de'lo ke'hai tanna, our משנה Mishnah is not
like the following תנא. Tanna. דתניא De'tanya it was taught in a
ברייתא, beraisa, רבי יהושע בנו של יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר אין בגידים
בנותן טעם, Rabbi Yehoshua beno shel Yochanan ben Beroka omer ein be'gidim
b'noten ta'am, גיד הנשה gid hanasheh does not have taste and if
you cook a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh in the thigh you do
not have to worry about the taste, you just remove the גיד
הנשה, gid hanasheh, it did not impart any taste. Now,
you might remember that there was an opinion before that said that
because it doesn't have taste, it can't be that's what the תורה
Torah forbade, and therefore the תורה Torah only forbade sort of the
branches, the קנוקנות, knoknot, but תוספות, Tosfos, you know, but the גמרא
Gemara does not strictly make those positions dependent on one another, and
you can say there was another opinion in the גמרא Gemara before
that said that no, עץ הוא והתורה אסרתו. etzu ve-Torah asarto. Yeah,
it's like a piece of wood, it has no taste, but doesn't
matter, that's what the תורה Torah forbade. So this seems to not
debate what is forbidden, it is the גיד gid that's forbidden, but
it just so happens that it has no taste and you don't
have to worry if you cooked it with other things. ההוא דאתא
לקמיה דרבי חנינא. A'hu de-asa lekamei de-Rabbi Chanina. Somebody came in front
of רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. I think that this coming גמרא Gemara
is one of the most important גמרות Gemaras in terms of the
idea of הלכה halakhic pluralism. So let's take a look. Somebody came
to רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. הוה יתיב רבי יהודה בר זבינא בבבא.
Hava yasiv Rabbi Yehuda bar Zvina b'vava. So רבי יהודה בר זבינא
Rabbi Yehuda bar Zvina was sitting by the on the doorstep there
of רבי חנינא's Rabbi Chanina house. And he saw somebody went into
רבי חנינא's Rabbi Chanina house to ask a שאלה. shaala. So כי
נפיק, ki nafik, when this person came out of רבי חנינא's Rabbi
Chanina house, אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
to him, מאי אמר לך? Mai amar lach? What did he, I'm
sorry, did I skip a line? Okay, so מאי אמר לך. Mai
amar lach. So what did he say to you? I guess he
understood that the question was that he had cooked a גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh together with the rest of the meat. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, so he said to him, שריא ניהלי. Sharya ni alei. He
told me that it was permissible. Presumably he פסק paskin-ed אין בגידין
בנותן טעם. ein begidim benosein taam. Yeah, he said
don't worry about it. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda did not like that answer, so he said to him, הדר
עייליה לקמיה. Hadar ailei lekamei. Go ask him again, maybe you misunderstood.
So he went in and he asked him again. אמר, Amar, he
said, so who
was it?
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said, מאן האי דקא מצער לי? Man hai
de-kameitzareili? Who's this that's giving me a hard time? Who sent you
back? זיל אימא ליה למאן דייתיב בבבא. Zil eimal lei leman de-yasiv
b'vava. This is what he said to the guy who asked him
the question, right? Because this guy, he's a פשוטע ייד, pashuteh yid,
so this rabbi tells him to go back and ask again, he
went back and asked again. So רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said who
who is this that's דרייען מיר א קאפ? draying me a kop?
Go tell that guy sitting out at the
doorstep, זיל אימא ליה למאן דייתיב בבבא. zil eimal lei leman de-yasiv
b'vava. This is what he said to the questioner, אין בגידין בנותן
טעם. ein begidim benosein taam. That גידין gidin don't have a taste
and you don't have to worry about it. I'm sorry if that's
not the way you rule, that's the way I rule, stop giving
me a hard time. Okay, כי אתו לקמיה דרבי אמי. ki asu
lekamei de-Rabbi Ammi. Now when people with these types of questions, it's
funny, כי אתו, ki asu, it's in the plural, like it sounds
like very often people would forget to remove the גיד הנשה. gid
hanasheh. I mean, remember that there was an earlier משנה Mishna that
questioned about whether you can trust the butchers. If you can't trust
the butchers and people have to do it on their own, you
have another problem, that people forget to do it. They bring a
whole thigh of beef home from the butcher, maybe they salt because
they remember to salt everything, but they might forget to remove the
גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh. Although תוספות Tosfos says that the סתם משנה
stam Mishna was you do trust the butchers. But it is interesting,
it seems that this was not a rare event. So when people
came, כי אתו לקמיה דרבי אמי, ki asu lekamei de-Rabbi Ammi, when
they came in front of רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi with this question,
משדר להו לקמיה דרבי יצחק בר חלוף. meshader lehu lekamei de-Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Chalov. He sent them, he says, you know what? I think
you'd be better off going asking רבי יצחק בר חלוף. Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Chalov. Don't ask me
this question. Why? דמורי בה להיתירא כרבי יהושע בן לוי. De-mori ba
le-heteira k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. רבי יצחק בר חלוף Rabbi Yitzchak bar
Chalov פסק paskins that it's מותר, muttar, he holds like רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi that says that it's not a
problem.
וליה לא סבירא ליה. Velei lo seveira lei. But he himself didn't
agree with that. He held it was אסור, assur, but he knew
that that's not the answer these people needed, so he referred them
to another rabbi who had a different פסק. psak. And that's why
I think this גמרא Gemara is fascinating because this is, I think,
one of the few גמרות, Gemaras, if any, that I know of
that reflect the idea that you can have a specific הלכה halakhic
position and at the same time say, this is my position but
it doesn't mean that everything else is wrong. Right? That there are,
now it doesn't mean that you can't say there's certain הלכה halakhic
positions are off the reservation. It doesn't mean that every הלכה halakhic
position that's ever is within the boundaries of אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים
חיים, eilu v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim, but it does mean that if
you you can acknowledge that there is a range of legitimate positions.
This is the one I hold, but me holding it does not
mean that everybody else is sinning and doing the wrong thing. And
which then also means that you can refer somebody to somebody else.
You can say, you know, I I know what I hold about
this, because that but I acknowledge that there are other positions out
there. You might be advised more to go to ask another שאלה.
shaala. So that's why I think that this גמרא Gemara is, you
know, one of the in my mind one of the strongest statements
of a type of a living אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים eilu
v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim because normally אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים eilu
v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim ends with והלכה כדברי בית הלל, ve-halakhah ke-divrei
Beis Hillel, which means that in theory there are potential ones, but
at the bottom line there's one legitimate. This sort of acknowledges, now
implicitly we acknowledge this every day when we say אשכנזים Ashkenazim do
this and ספרדים Sefardim do that. So we're not saying that the
ספרדים Sefardim all sinners or the אשכנזים Ashkenazim are all sinners because
they're doing the different thing. But I don't think I think it's
a little bit rarer to maybe as consciously acknowledge within a given
community that there are legitimate other opinions and to the point where
it's not even considered a compromise of my own religious or intellectual
integrity to refer somebody elsewhere. It would be a compromise of me
to פסק paskin against what I believe in, but not to say
there are other legitimate opinions you might want to ask someone else.
Okay, we'll just read the last line on this. והלכתא אין בגידין
בנותן טעם. V'hilch'sa ein begidin b'nosein ta'am. And that's surprising. You might
not have expected that, right? We had a whole big discussion about
the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh סתם משנה stam Mishnah and we actually
rule that גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh does not have taste, and if
you cook it in the בשר, basar, it is not a problem.
Now רש"י Rashi says there still is a problem with the חלב
cheilev of the גיד. gid. Remember there was a discussion about the
חומרא chumra about the חלב cheilev of the גיד? gid? So if
you cook it, it is a problem because the חלב cheilev gave
off taste unless you remove the חלב. cheilev. תוספות Tosfos says we're
not going to be more strict with the חלב cheilev than we
are with the גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. So if we say אין
בגידין בנותן טעם, ein begidin b'nosein ta'am, then we're not going to
be concerned about the taste given off by the fat that surrounds
the גיד. gid. So according to תוספות, Tosfos, in principle, you cook
the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh with the בשר, basar, just remove the
גיד, gid, no problem. We don't worry about the taste that it
gave off, we don't worry about the taste that the fat gave
off, and so on. Not לכתחילה. l'chatchila. I have a doubt לכתחילה,
l'chatchila, although you could, you know, it's an interesting question: why not
לכתחילה? l'chatchila? Why not לכתחילה? l'chatchila? We're not being לבטל איסור לכתחילה
l'vateil issur l'chatchila because no taste is coming off. It's an interesting
question, and maybe it makes it easier to remove. It's a fascinating
question whether once it's לא נותן טעם lo nosein ta'am you could
do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Now תוספות Tosfos has another problem because based
on a גמרא Gemara in פסחים, Psachim, the גמרא Gemara in פסחים
Psachim says based on its whole way of learning, which I'm not
going to bother you with right now, that if גיד הנשה Gid
Hanasheh doesn't have a taste, it would lead to a conclusion that
גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh is אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Now some, I
think the רמב"ם Rambam if I remember correctly, splits the vote, he
does not go by the גמרא Gemara in פסחים, Psachim,
but תוספות Tosfos says that you would have to follow that logic.
And therefore he says that therefore if we פסקן pasken that it
doesn't have taste, we are also פסקןing pasken that it's אסור בהנאה,
assur b'hana'ah, and that leads to a question about giving
a thigh with a גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh to a non-Jew, is
that considered deriving benefit, is it considered that the non-Jew sort of
is happier to get it with the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh and
therefore you're deriving some indirect benefit from that or not? That's a
discussion תוספות Tosfos has.
I don't see what the הנאה hana'ah would be from though if
we פסקן pasken that it has no taste.
Right, but maybe the הנאה hana'ah is that like the thigh looks
nicer, I don't know. So that's exactly what תוספות Tosfos discusses. He's
right, I mean but he basically says most of the times it
won't be a problem exactly for that reason. What do they care
if there's a גיד gid or not a גיד gid in it?
Rifty, you had a question before? No?
I answered by rabbi shopping, can the individual...
He wasn't shopping, the rabbi was referring.
But can an individual do that also?
So that is an important question about, you know,
some people sort of quote the idea of עשה לך רב asei
l'cha rav as a statement that you can't... we're not done, for
everybody that's closing up, but okay... of עשה לך רב asei l'cha
rav that you can't rabbi shop. But that's really not what that
means, it's a line from פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avos. You know, that
more has to do with, I would say, sort of say general
religious integrity. You know, the גמרא Gemara the גמרא Gemara for that
quotes a פסוק pasuk from the... a פסוק pasuk that says עמי
במקלו יגיד לו, ami b'maklo yagid lo, which is talking about like
necromancy, so
the גמרא Gemara makes a דרשה drasha on that: כל המקל לו
יגיד לו. kol hameikel lo yagid lo. מקל, makel, מקל, meikel, that
they are looking to find somebody that's being מקל. meikel. And there,
there really is a problem because that basically means that you're not
submitting yourself to the authority of הלכה, Halacha, you're basically saying I've
already decided what I'm going to do and I'm just going to
find somebody that tells me it's okay.
Not to the הלכה, Halacha, just not to a particular rabbi.
Oh, so it depends what you mean by rabbi shopping. If by
rabbi shopping you mean I want somebody to tell me it's מותר,
mutar, I'm going to find out who says it's מותר mutar and
then go to that person, then I don't think that's considered submitting
yourself to authority. If what you mean is that for these types
of questions I trust this rabbi, I trust his general approach here,
I trust his outlook, I trust his expertise, for other הלכות halachos
I go to somebody else, that I think is totally fine. There's
an idea there can be an idea of specialization also, some types
of things the question about a perspective certain people have on things
is relevant, like somebody once told me never ask a כשרות שאלה
kashrus shayla to a rabbi who doesn't enjoy his food. So
I don't know if that's always true, but you know like for
example like when you deal with הלכות נידה, Hilchos Niddah, some rabbis
have radically different perspectives about what are the values that are at
stake in terms of... so those types of issues, yes. But I
would say that if you basically go to one rabbi for your
הלכות נידה Hilchos Niddah questions, but you don't particularly... area his strength,
so when things come up in that area you're going to go
to a different rabbi, that I think is very problematic because that's
not really about, you know, about submitting to authority, that's about, you
know, just finding somebody who's going to tell you what you want
to do anyway is okay. So but you know... so that but
again so they're not like black and white הלכות halachos about that,
but I think that the basic question has to do with sort
of religious integrity. Yes. Okay, so let's just read a little bit
more here, although we did get to the end of the line,
but maybe we'll get a little bit ahead. גיד הנשה שנתבשל. Gid
Hanasheh shenisbashel.
So it now says that now we get to... you know what,
maybe we won't. Okay, it's really the end.
We got a couple of... just a real real short...
I know it's a real short one, but it's a very important
idea and I don't want to rush it. What time is it?
We'll end here, we'll pick up.